Ali Zain

↑ a-zain.github.io ☑ azain@email.sc.edu ☐ +1 857 204 9325 ☎ Google Scholar/Lq5X5LcAAAAJ

RESEARCH INTERESTS

My research interests are general areas of mass communication with an extensive focus on **online misinformation**, **information processing**, **digital discourse in politics and public relations**, and **health communication**. I use traditional qualitative and quantitative methods as well as more sophisticated *computational* and *psycho-physiological methods*. Moreover, I am interested in conducting **inter-disciplinary research** in collaboration with domain experts from computer science, public health, and marketing.

EDUCATION

University of South Carolina, Columbia (UofSC)

2020 – Present

May 2023 (Expected Graduation)

Ph.D. IN MASS COMMUNICATION

My doctoral dissertation uses self-report questionnaires and psychophysiological measures to assess the role of social media labels used by mainstream platforms (i.e., Facebook, Instagram, and Twitter) in countering the online spread of misinformation. Building on the Heuristic Systematic Model, this research examines how these labels facilitate heuristic or/and systematic information processing . During viewing, I map the paths of neural processing mechanisms (e.g., gaze fixation, gaze map, arousal, and brainwave activity) as well as the variables associated with persuasion (e.g., message and source credibility, sharing and verification intents, and subsequent social media engagement behavior). The findings are expected to provide recommendations for improvement and personalization of platforms' user-interfaces to make them more efficient in countering misinformation. Dissertation Committee:

Dr. Sei-Hill Kim (Chair), Dr. Jungmi Jun, Dr. Taylor Wen, and Dr. Amir Karami (Business School)

2018 – 2020

Hacettepe University, Ankara (HU)

M.A. IN COMMUNICATION SCIENCES

2011 – 2015 University of the Punjab, Lahore (PU)

B.S. IN COMMUNICATION STUDIES

PEER REVIEWED JOURNAL PUBLICATIONS

Jun, J., Fitzpatrick, MA., Zain, A. and Zhang, N. (2022). Have e-cigarette risk perception and cessation intent of young adult users changed during the Pandemic? *American Journal of Health Behaviors*, 46 (3), 304-314(11). https://doi.org/10.5993/AJHB.46.3.9

AJHB '22

nttps://doi.org/10.5993/AJHb.46.3.9

Jun, J., Zain, A., Chen, Y., Kim, S. H. (2022). Adverse mentions, negative sentiment, and emotions in covid-19 vaccine tweets and their association with vaccination uptake: global comparison of 192 countries. *Vaccines*, 10(5), 735. https://doi.org/10.3390/vaccines10050735

VACCINES '22

Dino Gidreta, A., Binark, M., Ozsu, G. and Zain, A. (2022). Trusts and doubts in Africa over Belt and Road Initiative: a thematic content analysis of opinions in Ethiopian twittersphere. *Etkileşim* 5(9), 12-35. DOI:

ETKILEŞIM '22

10.32739/etkilesim.2022.5.9.153

Jun, J., Zhang, N., Zain, A. and Mohammadi, E. (2022). Social media discussions on the FDA's modified risk tobacco product authorization of IQOS. Substance Use and Misuse 57(3), 472-480. DOI: 10.1080/10826084.2021.2019777

SU&M '22

Zain, A. (2021). (Re)Production of hindutva-driven populism in India: an analysis of Bharatiya Janata Party's

JAS '21

political messaging in twittersphere. The Journal of Asian Studies 5(2), 179-194. DOI: 10.34189/asyam.5.2.005

JAS '20	Zain, A., Ozsu, G., Binark, M. and Dino Gidreta, A. (2020). China-Pakistan Economic Corridor and technicians of opinion in Pakistani twittersphere: a thematic content analysis. <i>The Journal of Asian Studies</i> 4(1),9-28. DOI: 10.34189/asyam.4.1.002
Moment '19	<u>Zain, A.</u> (2019). Rise of Modi's tech-populism in India. <i>Moment Journal</i> 6(1),199-208. DOI: 10.17572/mj2019.1.199208

PEER REVIEWED CONFERENCE PRESENTATIONS

AEJMC '22

Zain, A. (2022, August). Moralization in polarized debate on COVID-19 vaccination: human-AI collaborative analysis of tweets. 105th Annual Association for Education in Journalism and Mass Communication Conference, Detroit, MI.

First Place Moeller Student Paper Award

Zain, A. and Long, J. (2022, August). Countering online misinformation: testing impact of state sponsorship labels on message credibility, verification intention and behavior. 105th Annual Association for Education in Journalism and Mass Communication Conference, Detroit, MI.

Zain, A. (2022, August). Spiral of silence 50 years later: conceptual and empirical new directions. 105th Annual Association for Education in Journalism and Mass Communication Conference, Detroit, MI.

Ittefaq, M., Zain, A., and Bokhari, H. (2022, May). Opioids as comedy: exploring topics, sentiments, and engagement in Last Week Tonight with John Oliver on YouTube. 72nd Annual International Communication Association Conference.

ICA '22 Paris, France.

AEJMC '22

Chen, Y., Long, J., Jun, J., Kim, S., Zain, A., and Piacentine, C. (2022, May). Anti-intellectualism amid the covid-19 pandemic: the dynamics of anti-Fauci discourse on Twitter. 72nd Annual International Communication Association

ICA '22 Conference. Paris, France.

AEJMCSEC '22 Zain, A. (2022, March). Online endorsed misinformation and climate change: using heuristic cues to assess perceived action of messages and sharing intentions. 47th Annual AEJMC Southeast Colloquium, Memphis, TN.

Top Student Paper Award

Jun, J. and Zain, A. (2022, February). Global comparison of covid-19 vaccination sentiments and emotions on Twitter: findings from 192 countries. 3rd National Big Data Health Sciences Conference. Columbia, SC

Zain, A. (2021, August). Using theory of planned behavior, and operationalization of political partisanship and belief in misinformation to predict individuals' intentions to quit social media. 104th Annual Association for Education in

AEJMC '21 Journalism and Mass Communication Conference, New Orleans, LA.

Jun, J., Fitzpatrick, MA., Zhang, N., and Zain, A. (2021, August). Has covid-19 impacted the risk perceptions and cessation intent of youth vapers? 104th Annual Association for Education in Journalism and Mass Communication

AEJMC '21 Conference, New Orleans, LA.

Zain, A. (2021, August). Celebrity capital and social movements: a textual analysis of Bollywood celebrities' tweets on 2020-21 Indian farmers' protest. 104th Annual Association for Education in Journalism and Mass Communication Conference,

AEJMC '21 New Orleans, LA.

UBSK '21

Kim, S., Zain, A., and Heo, Y. (2021, August). *Idealized science vs. scientific skepticism in South Korea: micro-level evidence for the two-cultures thesis.* 104th Annual Association for Education in Journalism and Mass Communication

AEJMC '21 Conference, New Orleans, LA.

Zain, A. (2021, February). Doctrine of hindutva and political discourse of India's Bharatiya Janata Party: an analysis of 2019 election campaign. 1st International Social Sciences Conference, Ankara, Turkey.

Ozsu, G., Zain, A., Binark, M. and Dino Gidreta, A. (2020, November). Technicians of opinion in Ethiopia, Pakistan, and Turkey and their tweets about Chinese vision of alternative globalization: a comparative content analysis. 17th International Symposium: Communication in the Millennium, Istanbul, Turkey. ISBN: 978-605-83703-9-5 CIM '20 Zain, A. (2019, November). Aging-friendly smartphones: analysis of smartphones user-interface to assess their usability among elderly citizens. Senex: 3rd Congress of Aging Studies for Graduate Students, Antalya, Turkey. **SENEX '19** Zain, A. and Soomro, A (2016, November). Cultural continuity and mass media: an analysis of leading online newspapers of Pakistan. 1st National Conference Emerging Trends and Challenges in Social Sciences, Multan, Pakistan. ETCSS'16 BOOKS & BOOK CHAPTERS Zain, A. (2020). Contact and sanction: use of cricket as diplomatic tool by India and Pakistan. In M. Binark (Ed.), Popular culture and media in Asia (pp. 411-440). um:ag Publications.ISBN: 978-605-7882-42-4 2020 Zain, A. (2020). Aging friendly smartphones. In Y. Dede and M. Figan (Ed.), Aging in digital culture and afterwards (pp. 297-314). Alternatif Bilisim Dernegi.ISBN: 978-605-80007-2-8 2020 Zain, A. and Khan, N. T. (2016). Muasharti Jamhooriat. Kettering Foundation. An Urdu translation of The Ecology of Democracy by David Mathews 2016 Under Review Publications Kim, S., Oh, S., Heo, Y., and Zain, A. (Under Review). Journalists' Conceptions of Professional Norms and Ethics in South Korea: Personal, Organizational, and Environmental Level Predictors. 2022 Ittefaq, M., Zain, A. and Hukhari, H. (Under Review). Opioids as comedy: exploring topics, sentiments, and engagement in Last Week Tonight with John Oliver on YouTube.. 2022 Zain, A. and Ciccarelli, C. (Under Review). Political partisanship and belief in misinformation: operationalizing theory of planned behavior to predict intentions to quit social media. 2022 Chen, Y., Long, J., Jun. J., Kim, S., Zain, A., and Piacentine, C. (Under Review). Anti-intellectualism amid the covid-19 pandemic: the dynamics of anti-Fauci discourse on Twitter. 2022 Zain, A. (Under Review). Celebrity capital and social movements: a textual analysis of Bollywood celebrities' tweets on 2020-21 Indian farmers' protest. 2021 IN-PROGRESS PROJECTS Countering online misinformation: a mixed methods approach to assess efficacy of social media labels. 2022-2023 Lead by: Ali Zain Current Stage: Stimuli Development Biometric responses and health outcomes of youth exposure to modified exposure claims for novel tobacco products with FDA authorization cues. 2021-2022

> Lead by: Dr. Jungmi Jun Current Stage: Data Analysis

This ad speaks to me: an investigation of mechanisms underlying social identity relevant advertising.

Lead by: Dr. Taylor Wen Current Stage: Data Analysis

2022 Anti-social disinformation on social media: the effects of information sources and message Framing.

Lead by: Dr. Sei-Hill Kim Current Stage: Pre-test

Young adults' responses to the tobacco industry's corporate social responsibility communication.

Lead by: Dr. Jungmi Jun Current Stage: Data Collection

PROFESSIONAL EXPERIENCE

2020 – Present 2014 – 2017

2021 - 2021

2020 - 2022

2020 - 2021

2022

2016

University of South Carolina (UofSC) Daily Pakistan (DP) GRADUATE RESEARCH ASSISTANT/INSTRUCTOR OF RECORD

CONTENT EDITOR

TEACHING INTERESTS

Communication Theory

· Communication Research Methods

- Digital Media & Big Data Analysis
- Health Communication

- Strategic Communication
- Public Opinion & Political Communication
- Social Media Analytics & Research
- · Communication & Persuasion

TEACHING EXPERIENCE

2021 – 2022 Account Planning: Mining Insights

Mass Communications Research

Public Relations Management

Communicating Science, Health and the Environment

Fall '21, Spring 22

Spring '21

FALL '20, FALL '21, SPRING '22

FALL '20, FALL '21

[Note on the teaching experience: I have taught all these courses as *Instructor of Record* and *Teaching Assistant* at the University of South Carolina. Teaching Evaluations and Teaching Philosophy are also available on request.]

AWARDS & HONORS

First Place Moeller Student Paper Award: For presenting "Moralization in Polarized Debate on COVID-19 Vaccination: Human-AI Collaborative Analysis of Tweets" at 105th annual Association for Education in Journalism and Mass Communication (AEJMC) conference (including 250 USD cash prize and waiver of conference registration fee worth 200 USD)

registration fee worth 200 USD)

Top Student Paper Award: For presenting "Online endorsed misinformation and climate change: using heuristic cues to assess perceived credibility of messages and sharing intentions" at 47th annual conference of AEJMC

2022 Southeast Colloquium

University Gold Medal: For securing highest CGPA in BS Communication Studies in the class of 2015

GRANTS & SCHOLARSHIPS

Mary Caldwell Graduate Scholarship: Graduate scholarship worth 9,000 USD for the doctoral program at University of South Carolina 2020 - 2023Junior Scholar Award: Training and research support worth 4, 500 USD awarded by South Carolina SmartState Center of Health Quality (CHQ) 2022 -2023Mass Communication and Society Travel Grant: To attend 105th annual Association for Education in Journalism and Mass Communication (AEJMC) Conference in Detroit, MI (1,000 USD) 2022 ICA 2022 Michael Haley Travel Grant: To attend 72nd International Communication Association Conference in Paris, France (400 USD) 2022 ICA 2022 Political Communication Division Travel Grant: To attend 72nd International Communication Association Conference in Paris, France (400 USD) 2022 Research Grant by Hacettepe University: For the transnational study of China's Belt and Road Initiative (3, 200 2019-2020 Turkiye Graduate Scholarship: Fully funded scholarship for MA in Communication Sciences at Hacettepe 2017-2020 University 2012-2015 PU Merit Scholarship: Awarded to 5 top-ranked students at University of the Punjab PROFESSIONAL TRAININGS & CERTIFICATIONS CHQ Junior Scholar Program: Extensive research traineeship offered by the SC SmartState Center for Health Quality to apply computational methods for research at the interaction of public health and social media 2022 - 2023Publication Process & Peer Review Training: Certificate program offered by the Journal of Mass Communication 2022 - 2023Quarterly (JMCQ) focused on formal manuscript review process training SHARPGrads Certificate: The Skills, Habits, and Research Program for Graduate Students offered by the UofSC Digital Research Services and Research Computing Institute focused on training workshops on computing, textual analysis, programming, and visualization tools 2021 Programming for Everybody: online Coursera program offered by University of Michigan focused on python programming 2021 Citi Certificate on Human Research: Training demonstration program for social and behavioral researchers offered by Citi Program 2021 HubSpot Social Media Maarketing: Certificate program offered by the HubSpot Academy focused on social media monitoring, content strategy, social engagement, creating social media policies, and demonstrating social ROI 2021 Google Analytics: Certificate program offered by the Google Analytics Academy focused on training

RESEARCH SKILLS

• R/RStats	• BrandWatch	• NodeXL	• Jupyter Notebook
• Python	• NVivo	• Advanced Excel	• SAS
• iMotions	• Qualtrics	• SEO	• Gephi

TALKS/GUEST LECTURES/MEDIA

demonstrations and activities to test online analytical skills

Countries with lower-than-expected vaccination rates show unusually negative attitudes to vaccines on Twitter shorturl.at/cHMY5

THE CONVERSATION

2021

2021	Use of new media technologies by populist right-wing political parties in India	HACETTEPE UNIVERSITY
2019	Ageing-friendly smartphones to overcome digital divide in aging societies	Akdeniz University
2017	Journalistic prospects of new media technologies	University of the Punjab

SERVICE TO THE FIELD

2022	Social Media + Society (SM+S)	Peer Reviewer
2022	JMIR Medical Informatics (JMI)	Peer Reviewer
2022	JMIR Formative Research (JFR)	Peer Reviewer
2022	Political Communication Division, Association for Education in Journalism and Mass Communication (AEJMC)	Peer Reviewer
2022	Graduate Student Interest Group, Association for Education in Journalism and Mass	I LLK KLVILWEK
2022	Communication (AEJMC)	Peer Reviewer
2021	Computational Communication Division, International Communication Association (ICA)	Peer Reviewer

REFERENCES

Sei-Hill Kim KIM96@MAILBOX.SC.EDU

Eleanor M. & R. Frank Mundy Professor School of Journalism and Mass Communication University of South Carolina 803-777-7037

Jungmi Jun JUNJ@MAILBOX.SC.EDU

Associate Professor School of Journalism and Mass Communication University of South Carolina 803-576-5982

Mary Anne Fitzpatrick

FITZPATM@MAILBOX.SC.EDU

Educational Foundation Distinguished Professor School of Journalism and Mass Communication University of South Carolina 803-777-4614